<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: vmware | Just Another Linux Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.chriscowley.me.uk/blog/categories/vmware/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.chriscowley.me.uk/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-17T14:07:40+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.chriscowley.me.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Chris Cowley]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[VMware CLI on Ubuntu Saucy Salamander]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.chriscowley.me.uk/blog/2014/04/09/vmware-cli-on-ubuntu-saucy-salamander/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-09T10:51:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.chriscowley.me.uk/blog/2014/04/09/vmware-cli-on-ubuntu-saucy-salamander</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="http://www.datanalyzers.com/VMware-Data-Recovery.jpg">The current project (as of this week) has me moving away from Openstack for a while. For the next couple of months I will be immersing myself in monitor, metrics and logging. Naturally, this being a shiney new environment, this involves a significant amount of VMware time.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I have inherited an Icinga install running on Ubuntu Server, so I will be needing to run CLI commands to create checks. Simply runnning the installer does not work, as the vmware-cli package is a mixture of 32 and 64 bit commands.</p>

<p>First you need to download the CLI from VMware. How to do that is an exercise for the reader, as I cannot be bothered to find the link (hint: it is not hard). Then you need to install a bunch of packages:</p>

<p><code>
sudo apt-get install cpanminus libdata-dump-perl libsoap-lite-perl libclass-methodmaker-perl  libxml-libxml-simple-perl libssl-dev libarchive-zip-perl libuuid-perl lib32z1 lib32ncurses5 lib32bz2-1.0
</code></p>

<p>This includes a bunch of Perl modules for munching through XML, plus some 32-bit libraries so that all the tools can work.</p>

<p>Finally, you can extract the tarball and install the CLI:</p>

<p><code>
tar xvf VMware-vSphere-CLI-5.5.0-1549297.x86_64.tar.gz
cd vmware-vsphere-cli-distrib/
sudo ./vmware-install.pl
</code></p>

<p>I have not tested it, but this will probably be the same process for Debian (at least Wheezy and Sid).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
