<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: programming | Just Another Linux Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.chriscowley.me.uk/blog/categories/programming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.chriscowley.me.uk/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-23T22:25:19+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.chriscowley.me.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Chris Cowley]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fixed my gihub repo list]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.chriscowley.me.uk/blog/2012/07/03/fixed-my-gihub-repo-list/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-03T20:54:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.chriscowley.me.uk/blog/2012/07/03/fixed-my-gihub-repo-list</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My Github repo list has not worked as all since I moved over to Octopress. This evening I though I would have a little look into it.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>It turned out that GitHub has <a href="https://github.com/blog/1160-github-api-v2-end-of-life" target="_blank">depreciated the version 1 and 2 APIs</a>. Octopress was using version 2, so I have made a little change.</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/3042647.js?file='></script>
<noscript><pre><code></code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>According to <a href="https://github.com/imathis/octopress/issues/620" target="_blank">this issue</a> there will be a fix in <a href="https://github.com/imathis/octopress/tree/2.1" target="_blank" >Octopress 2.1</a>. However, this patch will keep things working until Brandon Mathis moves it into the master branch. Of course that issue also highlighted the fact that I had just re-invented the wheel :(</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Back to basics]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.chriscowley.me.uk/blog/2012/02/22/back-to-basics/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-22T13:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.chriscowley.me.uk/blog/2012/02/22/back-to-basics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have been a Sys Admin for quite a while now. Specialising in Linux means that I am often called upon to be a “jack of all trades, master of many”. In the last week I have touched upon storage, multiple programming languages (Bash, PHP, Python, Ruby and Java), Linux, Exchange, Tomcat, Virtualization and Systems architecture. I am sure the list could go on … and on … and on …</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>There is however something that I feel I am missing. Before I was in my current post, I was more of a developer. I did a lot of Shell scripting, but also ADA and C/C++. Nowadays I do not do that, which is a shame. Virtually all modern programming languages trace their roots back to C and C++. The whole of Linux/UNIX traces its roots back to C. Our world is built on C/C++!</p>

<p>This is something I have neglected over recent years, so I’m going to change that. A bit of Google-fu just now has bought me some interesting resources:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;a href="http://www.cplusplus.com/doc/tutorial/" target="_blank" &gt;http://www.cplusplus.com/doc/tutorial/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.howtoforge.com/howtos/programming/c-cplusplus" target="_blank" &gt;http://www.howtoforge.com/howtos/programming/c-cplusplus&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.gtk.org/tutorial1.2/" target="_blank" &gt;http://www.gtk.org/tutorial1.2/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://zetcode.com/tutorials/qt4tutorial/" target="_blank" &gt;http://zetcode.com/tutorials/qt4tutorial/&lt;/a&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>I have not looked at any of these in detail yet, but I will be over the next few days. At the end I hope to have dragged this hard-earned knowledge kicking and screaming from the back of my mind.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
